By raising your hand,
برفع الأيدي،
how many of you know at least one person on the screen?
كم منكم يعرف على الأقل شخصا واحدا في الشاشة؟
Wow, it's almost a full house.
عظيم، الجميع تقريبا.
It's true, they are very famous in their fields.
هذا صحيح،إنهم مشهورون في مجالات عملهم.
And do you know what all of them have in common?
و هل تعلمون ما هو الشيء المشترك بينهم؟
They all died of pancreatic cancer.
كلهم ماتوا بسبب سرطان البنكرياس.
However, although it's very, very sad this news,
ومع ذلك، على الرغم من ان هذه الأخبار محزنة جداَ،
it's also thanks to their personal stories
أيضاَ و بفضل قصصهم الشخصية
that we have raised awareness of how lethal this disease can be.
أثرنا الإنتباه حول فتك هذا المرض.
It's become the third cause of cancer deaths,
أصبح السبب الثالث من الوفيات الناجمة عن السرطان،
and only eight percent of the patients will survive beyond five years.
وثمانية في المئة فقط من المرضى سيبقون على قيد الحياة لأكثرمن خمسة أعوام.
That's a very tiny number,
وهذا رقم صغير جداَ،
especially if you compare it with breast cancer,
خاصة إذا قارنته مع سرطان الثدي،
where the survival rate is almost 90 percent.
حيث يبلغ معدل البقاء على قيد الحياة ما يقرب من 90 في المئة.
So it doesn't really come as a surprise
لذلك لا يعتبر بالمفاجئ
that being diagnosed with pancreatic cancer
أن كونك مصابا بسرطان البنكرياس
means facing an almost certain death sentence.
يعني تقريباَ مواجهة حكم مؤكد بالإعدام.
What's shocking, though, is that in the last 40 years,
ما هو صادم،من ذلك هو أن في 40 عاماَ،
this number hasn't changed a bit,
هذا الرقم لم يتغير قليلاَ،
while much more progress has been made
بينما تم إحراز تقدم أكثر
with other types of tumors.
مع أنواع أخرى من الأورام.
So how can we make pancreatic cancer treatment more effective?
فكيف يمكننا أن نجعل علاج سرطان البنكرياس أكثر فعالية؟
As a biomedical entrepreneur,
كأحد الرواد في الطب الحيوي،
I like to work on problems that seem impossible,
أود العمل على حل المشاكل التي تبدو مستحيلة،
understanding their limitations
فهم حدودها
and trying to find new, innovative solutions
و محاولة إيجاد حلول جديدة مبتكرة
that can change their outcome.
التي يمكن أن تغير نتائجها.
The first piece of bad news with pancreatic cancer
أول خبر من الأخبار السيئة المتعلقة بسرطان البنكرياس
is that your pancreas is in the middle of your belly, literally.
هو أن البنكرياس حرفياَ،في منتصف بطنك.
It's depicted in orange on the screen.
هو مُبين باللون البرتقالي على الشاشة.
But you can barely see it
ولكن بالكاد يمكن أن تراه
until I remove all the other organs in front.
حتى إزالة جميع الأعضاء الاخرى في المقدمة.
It's also surrounded by many other vital organs,
أنه محاط أيضاَ بالعديد من الأعضاء الحيوية الأخرى،
like the liver, the stomach, the bile duct.
مثل الكبد والمعدة و القناة الصفراوية.
And the ability of the tumor to grow into those organs
وقدرة الورم على النمو والوصول لتلك الأجهزة
is the reason why pancreatic cancer
هو السبب في أن سرطان البنكرياس
is one of the most painful tumor types.
هو واحد من أكثر أنواع الأورام إيلاماَ.
The hard-to-reach location also prevents the doctor
صعوبة الوصول لمكانه ولأنه أيضاَ يمنع الطبيب
from surgically removing it,
من إزالته جراحياَ،
as is routinely done for breast cancer, for example.
كشيء يحدث روتينياَ لسرطان الثدي، على سبيل المثال.
So all of these reasons leave chemotherapy as the only option
لذلك كل من هذه الأسباب تجعل العلاج الكيميائي هو الخيار الوحيد
This brings us to the second piece of bad news.
هذا يقودنا للخبر السيئ الثاني.
Pancreatic cancer tumors have very few blood vessels.
للأورام السرطانية في البنكرياس عدد قليل جداَ من الأوعية الدموية.
Why should we care about the blood vessel of a tumor?
لماذا علينا أن نهتم بالأوعية الدموية للورم؟
Let's think for a second how chemotherapy works.
دعونا نفكر للحظة واحدة في كيفية عمل العلاج الكيميائي.
The drug is injected in the vein
يتم حقن الدواء في الوريد
and it navigates throughout the body until it reaches the tumor site.
ويتنقل في جميع أنحاء الجسم حتى تصل إلى موقع الورم.
It's like driving on a highway, trying to reach a destination.
انها مثل القيادة على الطرق السريعة، في محاولة للوصول إلى الوجهة.
But what if your destination doesn't have an exit on the highway?
ولكن ماذا لو كانت وجهتك ليس لها مخرج على الطريق السريع؟
You will never get there.
لن تصل لذلك.
And that's exactly the same problem
وهذا بالضبط نفس المشكلة
for chemotherapy and pancreatic cancer.
للعلاج الكيميائي لسرطان البنكرياس.
The drugs navigate throughout all of your body.
الأدوية ستنتقل بكامل جسمك.
They will reach healthy organs,
ستصل الى الأعضاء السليمة،
resulting in high toxic effect for the patients overall,
مسببة تأثير سُمي عالي للمريض عموماَ،
but very little will go to the tumor.
ولكن القليل جداَ سوف يذهب إلى الورم.
Therefore, the efficacy is very limited.
ولذلك، فإن الفعالية محدودة للغاية.
To me, it seems very counterintuitive to have a whole-body treatment
بالنسبة لي،يبدو متوقع جداًَ أن يتم علاج الجسم بأكمله
to target a specific organ.
لاستهداف عضو معين.
However, in the last 40 years,
ومع ذلك، في السنوات ال 40 الماضية،
a lot of money, research and effort have gone towards
الكثير من المال، والبحوث و الجهد بذلت في سبيل
finding new, powerful drugs to treat pancreatic cancer,
إيجاد أدوية جديدة و مؤثرة لعلاج سرطان البنكرياس،
but nothing has been done in changing the way
و لكن لم يتم عمل شيء في تغيير الطريقة
we deliver them to the patient.
التي تقدم للمصاب.
So after two pieces of bad news,
لذلك بعد جزئين من الأخبار السيئة،
I'm going to give you good news, hopefully.
سأقدم لكم أخبار جيدة، على ما آمل.
With a collaborator at MIT
بالتعاون مع معهد ماساتشوستس
and the Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston,
ومستشفى ماساتشوستس العام في بوسطن،
we have revolutionized the way we treat cancer
أحدثنا ثورة في طريقة علاج السرطان
by making localized drug delivery a reality.
بإنتاج علاج موضعي التسليم.
We are basically parachuting you on top of your destination,
نحن جوهرياَ نُسقطكم على أعلى وجهتكم،
avoiding your having to drive all around the highway.
تجنباَ للاضطرار للقيادة على جميع أنحاء الطريق السريع.
We have embedded the drug into devices that look like this one.
يتم تضمين العلاج في أجهزة تبدو مثل هذه.
They are flexible enough that they can be folded
إنها مرنة لدرجة أنه بالإمكان طيها
to fit into the catheter,
لتناسب القسطرة،
so the doctor can implant it directly on top of the tumor
لذلك يمكن للطبيب زرعها مباشرة على الجزء العلوي من الورم
with minimally invasive surgery.
بالحد الأدنى من الجراحة.
But they are solid enough that once they are positioned
لكنها صلبة كفاية حيث أنه بمجرد أن يتم وضعها
on top of the tumor,
بمقدمة الورم،
they will act as a cage.
تعمل بمثابة قفص.
They will actually physically prevent the tumor
واقعياَ سيمنعون الورم مادياَ
from entering other organs,
من الوصول للأعضاء الأخرى،
controlling the metastasis.
والسيطرة على الورم الخبيث.
The devices are also biodegradable.
الأعضاء أيضاَ قابلة للتحلل.
That means that once in the body,
هذا يعني أنه بمجرد دخولها الجسم،
they start dissolving,
تبدأ بالذوبان،
delivering the drug only locally, slowly and more effectively
ناقلاة العلاج فقط موضعياَ و ببطئ و بفعالية أكثر
than what is done with the current whole-body treatment.
من ما يحدث عند العلاج الكامل للجسم.
In pre-clinical study, we have demonstrated
في دراسة قبل السريرية، أثبتنا
that this localized approach
أن هذه المقاربة الموضعية
is able to improve by 12 times the response to treatment.
قادرة على تحسين حتى نسبة 12 مرة الاستجابة للعلاج.
So we took a drug that is already known
لذلك أخذنا العلاج المعروف مسبقاَ
and by just delivering it locally where it's needed the most,
وقمنا فقط بتوصيله موضعياَ للمكان الذي يحتاجه أكثر،
we allow a response that is 12 times more powerful,
أعطينا الفرصة لإستجابة أكثرة فعالية ب12 مرة،
reducing the systemic toxic effect.
و حدّينا من تأثير السم المنظم.
We are working relentlessly to bring this technology to the next level.
نحن نعمل بكل جدّي لأيصال هذه التكنولوجيا الى مستوى أعلى.
We are finalizing the pre-clinical testing
و نضع اللمسات الأخيرة على التجارب قبل السريرية
and the animal model required prior to asking the FDA for approval
والنموذج الحيواني يتطلب موافقة ادارة الاغذية والعقاقير
for clinical trials.
للتجارب السريرية.
Currently, the majority of patients will die from pancreatic cancer.
حالياَ،غالبية المرضى سيموتون من سرطان البنكرياس.
We are hoping that one day,
آملين الوصول لليوم الذي
we can reduce their pain, extend their life
نكون قادرين على تخفيف آلامهم، و تمديد حياتهم
and potentially make pancreatic cancer
وربما جعل سرطان البنكرياس
a curable disease.
مرضا قابل للشفاء.
By rethinking the way we deliver the drug,
بإعادة التفكير بالطريقة التي نوصل فيها العلاج،
we don't only make it more powerful and less toxic,
نحن لا تجعلها أكثر قوة وأقل سُمية فقط،
we are also opening the door to finding new innovative solutions
نحن أيضاَ نفتح الباب لإيجاد حلول جديدة مبتكرة
for almost all other impossible problems
لكل المشاكل المستحيلة الأخرى تقريباَ
in pancreatic cancer patients and beyond.
لمرضى سرطان البنكرياس وغيرهم.
Thank you very much.
شكراَ جزيلاَ.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)